Lowell Thomas Film Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
- 13. Tibet, 1942-1969; 427 cans
  - L.T. & Bijou Tk Sync/Pix Sync, 1949; 51 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1111)
    The film showed Lowell Thomas walking with a woman and talking to her with children surrounding them; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - LT - Aufs & Kids Pix/TK, 1968; 91 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1114)
    On the audio track you can hear men asking children if they knew someone. You hear Lowell Thomas talking to a man about living in Tibet and the Himalayas and they were also talking about writing a book; Format: 16mm; Picture:; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Lowell Thomas 31012, 1942; 422 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1393)
    A man and woman speak to the Dalai Lama.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Dalai Lama, 1963; 917 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1394)
    Buddhist monks praying; Parthankot; passing out food and toys to children; man with a rosary spinning a prayer wheel; procession of elephants; His Holiness the 14th Dalai Lama with a man and woman; outdoor medical clinic; people laboring outside; and men and women weaving rugs and textiles on looms at the Tibetan Refugees Handicrafts Training Production.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Dalai Lama, 917 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1395)
  - Himalayan flute Nepal L. Thomas- show 1 "Tibet" Reel 4 Mus., 599 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1396)
    On the audio track you can hear people singing and you hear instruments being played.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color, Black & White, N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - High Adventure Tibet Music Outs 1: TRB2 Start Tibet Ritual Music Side 2 Cut 2; 2: Nepal R1 Mus A 87.682-693 Nepalese Drums; 3: 22-30 Nepal Drums R1 FXA; 4: Village: 16 7-32 Woman Singing Nepal R1 Mus A; 5: 36 4-7 Gong Nepal R1 MRA 3; 6: Grrd Nepal R1 Mus C 86 Nepalese Chanting 643-658; 7: Yak Music 22.238-258 Nepal R1 Mus A; 8: Sole Sherpa; 9: Band 2 Prayer Chant TLS Music 2; 10: Solo Girl B-4; 11: Connie Music Sherpas #2 Shot; 12: Monks, 928 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1397)
    People chant and sing in a different language, at times in a group and other times, solo. In between vocal recordings are recordings of musical instruments being played mainly the drums.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - TR A1, Girls & band, Funeral Type music Monks chant, Glee Club, Ding Aline & others, Nepal R. 1 Music, Nepal R 2 Music Nepal Chanting, Bass Slow, Big Horn, Nepal Buddhist Singer, 997 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1398)
    Ritual Music with horns, drums and gongs. Sounds of people chanting and singing along with the music.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Tibet, 1964; 1025 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1399)
    Part one of "High Adventure with Lowell Thomas" episode in Tibet. Narrated, produced, and directed by Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas, Jr. An Odyssey Production. Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas, Jr. are granted permission to enter Tibet prior to China's invasion. This film follows their journey across the Himalayas from India into Tibet, as they make their way to Lhasa in time for the summer festival. Contains introduction by Lowell Thomas.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - Tibet/Out of this World, 1964; 811 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1400)
    Part two of "High Adventure with Lowell Thomas" episode in Tibet. Narrated, produced, and directed by Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas, Jr. An Odyssey Production. Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas, Jr. arrive in Lhasa to meet His Holiness the 14th Dalai Lama and film him for the first time. On the journey home, Lowell Thomas breaks his hip [really his leg just below his hip] in eight places and must be carried back to India. Contains conclusion by Lowell Thomas.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - AK4000 #20, 852 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1401)
    Background audio of a Tibetan classroom.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Thymboche-Costume Dance-Tibetian Horns, Monks Etc., Sych Outs, and Trk Outs, 592 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1402)
    Monks quietly chanting. Horns being played. Prayers being read and spoken out loud. Lava dance at Thymboche.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Ihymboche Gong, 514 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1403)
    Audio of a monk ringing a gong and chanting.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Sherpa Country, Pokhara, 1969; 688 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1404)
    The film showed boys herding donkey's, showed children carrying things on their back, showed people working, and showed people sitting down. The film showed people washing clothes, showed people rowing a boat, showed someone cooking, it showed a girl making a necklace out of roses, it showed trees and mountains and it showed a plane landing.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Sherpa Country, Pokhara, 434 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1405)
    The film showed people walking up a hill carrying things on their back, it showed people taking pictures, it showed women, children and men smiling and talking. The film showed flowers and mountains.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - unlabeled, 1949; 883 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1406)
    The film showed a man with two cows, it showed people carrying things on their back and shoulders. The film showed children in top of rocks, it showed people walking up a hill, it showed mountains, it showed children running, it showed houses, it showed people walking in the streets and it showed people plowing the ground. The film showed at the market buying and selling things and it showed a woman braiding her hair.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - unlabled, 1949; 873 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1407)
    Three crows climb on a resting yak. Tibetan monks walk to the temple. Landscape shots of mountains. Hikers follow a trail down the mountain.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Unlabled, 1949; 977 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1408)
    Shots of daily farm life in Tibet. Landscape shots of the nearby snow covered mountains. Cut to monks chanting and reading from scrolls.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Out of this world, 1964; 1280 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1409)
    Appears to be first part of print of "Out of This World: Inside Forbidden Tibet" by Lowell Thomas, Jr. This film follows Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas, Jr. on their journey into Tibet toward Lhasa, including scenes of lamyik and white scarf exchange. Includes title scene.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Out of this World, 1950; 1118 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1410)
    Title scenes: "Out of This World: Inside Forbidden Tibet" by Lowell Thomas, Jr.; men riding horses; mosque; flying small plane; Sealdah Main Station; and first part of trip into Tibet. Some scenes separated by long stretches of leader.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Out of this world, 1965; 985 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1411)
    Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas, Jr. making their way into Tibet and arriving in Lhasa to witness a festival.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Out of this world, 1965; 1080 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1412)
    Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas, Jr. in Tibet. Notable scenes include the Panchen Lama, Potala, and His Holiness the 14th Dalai Lama in Lhasa, Lowell Thomas being carried out of Tibet on a stretcher; and Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas, Jr. exiting a Pan-Am plane after their journey.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Original Recordings, 430 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1413)
  - In Tibet, 1958; linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1414)
    Men travelling with donkeys - mountains in background, animal statue, close-up of faces, unknown object, make-shift carriage outdoors, buildings on top of mountains, man standing, pile of rubble, "High Adventures with Lowell Thomas", "50th anniversary", "Delco-Remy", "United Motors System", statue in front of mountains, buildings at bottom of mountains, cultural objects on table, men dressed in traditional clothing - monks praying - Lowell Thomas sitting with them, "USSR - Tibet" map, mountains, people travelling with donkeys, aerial view of terrain, men resting/gathered, close-up of people, men carrying luggage, donkeys, men looking at landscape, travelling - on bridge, wooden buildings, men talking, in front of mountains, crossing log bridge, large stone wall, buffalo/cows?, men with donkeys and luggage, close-up of men- gathering/campsite/travelling, people walking in town, Tibetan men with Lowell Thomas, man holding puppies, stone structures, men packing/talking, CBS sign, men travelling- in boat, people talking, cloth producing machine, man sitting, two men talking, men with luggage - travelling/talking/landscapes, town with buildings, travelling, Tibetan people walking/talking - dressed in cultural clothing, building with steeple - monks entering, cultural sculptures, monks sitting, some sort of ritual occurring, large crowd, men in masks.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - Tibet, 1945; linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1415)
    Countdown, man travelling with packed mules, a robed man speaks to a crowd of similarly robed men, castle-like city/temple on a mountain, High Adventure With Lowell Thomas, temple pillar with mountains in background, an engraved pot in the center of a stage, man sitting on a throne at the feet of a huge statue, man in headdress sitting with men and women similarly clothed, 2 monks walking together, 1 monk doing something with a string of beads, a young man facing camera, 3 older men sitting in a decorated room, man in european clothing (LT?) facing camera from decorated room, map of Asia, Tibet highlighted and zoomed in to, men leading packed mules through the mountains, man standing alone setting up camp, another man washing his hair with a waterfall?, men sitting/standing around camp, a man caring for the mules, men talking (close-ups on each of them), man with a backpack looking into the mountains, men with packs cross a suspension bridge, scene of a group of buildings, a group of men talking (more close-ups), a gilded door or window?, a similarly gilded ornament on a man's hat, a group of men talking, the men lead the mules away, men walking barefoot, large animals walking around, men setting up camp again, men talking, men leading the mules away again, High Adventure With Lowell Thomas.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - Tibet, 1957; 862 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1575)
    Audio only. Lowell Thomas is speaking to us from the Dalai Lama's Palace. He describes the palace for us in detail. Then he changes subject and discusses how he fell in love with production and adventure films. He wants to convert Cinerama movies to Television. He passes the focus on to his friend named Pat. Pat speaks of Lowell Thomas' achievements and talents. He discusses plans for new Television program plots. One about new countries that have been established since the end of World War II. Lowell Thomas comes back and goes on to list more movie ideas. Pat cuts him off, claiming they will run out of film. They wrap up, taking about how important and impactful real-world stories could be as entertainment.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - Tibet, 1957; 797 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1576)
    No audio. Lowell Thomas speaks to the camera (from behind a man with a long horn instrument wearing ceremonial clothing) for the first fifteen minutes of the roll. The remainder of the roll is blacked out film.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Tibet, 1945; 1825 linear feet 1 2000ft (16mm) (Can 1606)
    Full episode of "High Adventure with Lowell Thomas" in Tibet. Narrated, produced, and directed by Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas, Jr. An Odyssey Production. Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas, Jr. are granted permission to enter Tibet prior to China's invasion. This film follows their journey across the Himalayas from India into Tibet, as they make their way to Lhasa to meet His Holiness the 14th Dalai Lama and film him for the first time. On the journey home, Lowell Thomas breaks his hip [really his leg just below his hip] in eight places and must be carried back to India. Contains introduction and conclusion by Lowell Thomas.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - Out of this world, 1964; 1425 linear feet 1 2000ft (16mm) (Can 1607)
    Appears to be complete or nearly complete second part of print of "Out of This World: Inside Forbidden Tibet" by Lowell Thomas, Jr. This film follows Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas, Jr. as they arrive in Lhasa. Notable scenes include the festival, Panchen Lama, Potala, and His Holiness the 14th Dalai Lama in Lhasa, Lowell Thomas being carried out of Tibet on a stretcher; and Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas, Jr. exiting a Pan-Am plane after their journey.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Seven Wonders out takes 650', Yankee approximately 1350' - Lowell Thomas with Mr. Ralston '950, 2 reels reel a - b/w seven wonders of the world color outs - outside 1300' is Yankee. Reel B- color lowell thomas with Mr. Ralston 6/16/57, 1952; 1866 linear feet 1 2000ft (16mm) (Can 1608)
    Several scenes and takes of Lowell Thomas talking in front of multiple backdrops inside the same house, including a globe with him pointing to northern Africa, a large map, and a picture of the Potala in Lhasa, Tibet. These scenes are followed by Lowell Thomas addressing a small group of people on the deck of a sailboat. On that sailboat, a strong man lifts a woman over his head with one arm.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Tibet, 1957; linear feet 1 2000ft (35mm) (Can 1762)
    Two horse faces up close, men ride horses towards mountains, a man stands at the edge of frame, closeup on men with horses, 7 men standing in a line, a large crowd with horses, men ride horses to the mountain, two people with packs walk off frame, a man rides horse towards river, two men in turbans stand on either side of man in brimmed hat, man in turban looks around, religious statue, horses on edge of frame, crowd of people and cow walk, a person in turban and skirt stands, four people stand outside house, man in sweater, 3 people riding horses, airplane, men disembark plane, man walking with horse, crowd of men around man in robe, man in hat adjusts horse's pack closeup on man smiling, 3 men in hooded robes, engraved stone, crowd of people and horses, man in religious garb gesturing.; Format: 35mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - Arctic/Tibet (mix trk.), 1954; 1997 linear feet 1 2000ft (35mm) (Can 1763)
    Lowell Thomas discusses his travel to Tibet with his son, Lowell, jr. They have been invited by the Dalai Lama, but are not able to bring anyone else along with them. He describes the Tibetan people as peaceful isolationists and describes their journey through a small, simple town in the valley, where they meet a military escort. As they get closer to the city of Lhasa, Thomas describes the treacherous baths. He describes the city of Lhasa, calling it the ‘El Dorado’ of travelers. They visit a monastery with 10,000 monks and he describes their lifestyle. The then meet the Dalai Lama’s family, and finally the man himself. When they leave, Lowell Thomas is injured by an unruly horse. Lowell, jr. takes over and he describes the rest of the descent from the city. He describes the way that his father is strapped to a litter and carried for the rest of the journey. He details his fathers condition and how perilous it made the journey. Lowell Thomas takes over the end of the recording and credits his son for getting him out of danger.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Tibet', 1954; 1444 linear feet 1 2000ft (35mm) (Can 1764)
    The audio records people speaking in a different language, a tiger's growl, horses trotting, and an engine clanging.; Format: 35mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - L. Thomas Show 2 'Tibet' Reel 4 Mus B, 1953; 1,488 linear feet 1 2000ft (35mm) (Can 1765)
    Several audio clips of music. Men singing, chimes in the background. Crashing of symbols, droning horns. Crashing symbols again, as well as higher pitched horns. A group singing. Clarinet and a electronic piano.; Format: 35mm; Picture: Color, Black & White; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - L. Thomas High Adventure Arctic/Tibet Narration Track R5 Theatrical, 2003 linear feet 1 2000ft (35mm) (Can 1766)
    Lowell Thomas narrates his travel from Australia to Station A in the north pole, his crew included people like his son, Sir Hubert Wilkins, and Colonel Vulcan, Lowell Thomas gets invited to Tibet by the Dalai Llama and goes on a 24 day journey with his son, explores their culture, geography, and customs; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - L. Thomas Show 2 Reel 4 "Tibet" Mus. A, 1475 linear feet 1 2000ft (35mm) (Can 1767)
    Audio of a person playing the gong. Cut to a person playing a tune on a sitar/ sarod.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Cap Cities Tibet R4 Show 2 FX-A, 1954; 1444 linear feet 1 2000ft (35mm) (Can 1768)
    The audio records a gong, crunching leaves, bubbling water, kids playing, wind, hooves, and a ringing bell as a wagon is being pushed.; Format: 35mm; Picture: Color, N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Capital Cities-Lowell Thomas "Tibet" Reel 4 Show #2 FX "B" TRK, 1446 linear feet 1 2000ft (35mm) (Can 1769)
    Sound effects track of wind whistling and water splashing. Men singing and playing instruments. Crowds singing and chanting prayers.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Arctic/Tibet Slop Print, 1957; 1988 linear feet 1 2000ft (35mm) (Can 1770)
    Clips from both Tibet and the Arctic. The first set of clips is from the arctic. LT is narrating an expedition that he took with old polar explorers to the North Pole. They fly over glaciers and their first stop is a Island of ice with in the arctic circle. The island is a scientific station. LT talks to an Austrian scientist who says he studying how the ice melts. Another scientist speaks about how the ice can suddenly crack, splitting building apart. there are a couple of clips of men in wet suits jumping into the ice water. The trip continues-- LT along with the retired polar explorers fly over the north pole. One of the men is the only serving member of the historic Perry expedition. LT gives a champagne toast to this man as they fly over the north pole, because he has finally reached it after 48 years. LT also drops flowers as they fly over the pole, to honor all those that had lost their lives trying to reach it. Tibet-- the Tibet trip starts in India. LT and LT jr., along with Tibetan porters. load up pack animals in preparation of crossing the Himalayas to reach Tibet. They trek down cliff and over rivers. Everyone gets lice. Footage shows LT trying to wash away the lice in a waterfall. When they reach the first Tibetan village that mayor, who is 10 feet tall, comes out to greet them giving them silk scarfs. In the village they see women weaving and making butter. They see a herd of yaks on on a large plain. They make it to Lhasa. Officials comes to greet LT, and they they will be the hosts.s There is a festival in the city. There are giant horns and symbols crashing. There is a dance performance where the dancers are masked. They go to the largest monastery. there they see monks giving out barley flour to the poor. LT is finally allowed to meet the Dalai Lama. He is on a throne and asks them many questions. They then leave Lhasa via river. On the trek back to India, LT breaks his hip in eight places. He is then carried on a stretcher, and spends many days in pain.; Format: 35mm; Picture: Black & White, N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - L. Thomas Show 1 'Tibet' Reel 4 Mus C, 1953; 1,480 linear feet 1 2000ft (35mm) (Can 1771)
    Audio clips. Faint drumming and yelling. A man chanting. A low flute/trumpet. Symbols being played as a crescendo. A group of men chanting in a drone.; Format: 35mm; Picture: Color, Black & White; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Tibet, 542 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 3358)
    no audio. Slight sound of people rustling.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Tibet, 1955; 302 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 3359)
    Audio clip of a scene from a feature length mystery movie.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Tibet Narration, 1965; 818 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 3360)
    On the audio track you hear Lowell Thomas Jr. and Lowell Thomas talking about Tibet and no was able to penetrate the land of the last horizon in Lasso. They talked about how long it to took them to journey there and they talked about the people Tibet.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Tibet Narration, 1954; 579 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 3361)
    An adult event "The Climax". Scenes from a twinkie commercial.; Format: 35mm; Picture: Color, Black & White, N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Tibet Narration, 211 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 3362)
    On the audio track you can hear Lowell Thomas talking about the world of lofty mountains, he mentioned Buddhism and Asia.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Tibet Narration, 816 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 3363)
    On the audio track you hear Lowell Thomas talking about how China wants Tibet. He talked about Buddhism beliefs and Nirvana.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Tibet Narration, 965 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 3364)
    Lowell describes his Adventure in Tibet, the livelihood of the people and his experiences abroad. Yaks grazing on wild orchids, women weaving wool and sifting flour.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Tibet, 1946; 667 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 3365)
    Lowell Thomas interviews a man in North Africa. The man does not answer in English.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Tibet Narration, 1954; 936 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 3366)
    Lowell Thomas narrates a high adventure about his experience at a Tibetan New Year Festival. They performed a 16th century reenactment retelling the tale of the Knights of the Dalai Lama.; Format: 35mm; Picture: Color, N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Tibet - Monastary Horns, 411 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 3367)
    On the audio track you can hear different instruments being played.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Birds, Tibetan Gong, Monic Brm Bin, Gong, 255 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 3368)